February 27, 1943, Berlin, Germany. The Nazi regime launches a large-scale operation.
called "Fabrikaktion" to capture the last remaining Jews in the city and send them to
concentration camps. At that time, there were thousands of Jews in the German capital who, until
At that time, they had been saved from previous deportations thanks to their efforts as workers.
forced into the arms industry. In the coming weeks, most of this workforce
will be loaded onto cattle cars and transported to Auschwitz, where she will perish in the gas chambers.
However, some Jews manage to avoid capture, go into hiding and, with false documents,
They try to survive in hiding. However, the possibility of their survival
is reduced by the presence of the so-called "hunters", that is, Jewish collaborators who,
temporary security exchange, they help the Nazi secret police, the Gestapo, hunt down hidden Jews.
The most successful of these hunters operating in Berlin is Stella Goldschlag.
Stella Ingrid Goldschlag was born on July 10, 1922 in Berlin, then part of
of the Weimar Republic, the name given to the German democratic government between 1918 and 1933.
Stella grew up in the western part of Berlin, enjoying a typical childhood.
full of pretty dresses and the care of overprotective parents who affectionately nicknamed her
"Pünktchen", meaning "little dot", as she was the center of his world. Although the
The Goldschlag family celebrated the important Jewish holidays and were fully integrated into the
Teutonic society so they considered themselves Germans. Stella's father, Gerhard Goldschlag, a veteran
After the First World War, he worked as a conductor, composer and journalist.
Meanwhile, her mother, Antonie, pursued a singing career before getting married.
The Goldschlag family often had financial problems and sometimes had to resort to
social assistance as Stella's father struggled to find stable work.
Stella attended elementary school before enrolling in the School
Hohenzollern Girls' High School. On January 30, 1933, Adolf Hitler
He was appointed Chancellor of Germany by President Paul von Hindenburg.
Shortly thereafter, the Nazi regime began to implement its radical anti-Jewish agenda.
and in April of the same year the Law for the Restoration of the Professional Civil Service was approved,
dismissing Hebrew professionals from their government positions. This
Radical politics marked the beginning of widespread discrimination
which affected countless Jewish families, including the Goldschlags.
Stella's father, who worked for the news company Gaumont,
He lost his job during this time, plunging the family into financial difficulties.
By 1935, Jewish children like Stella were no longer allowed to attend school.
state. As a result, she was enrolled at the Goldschmidt School in Berlin,
a prestigious private institution that housed about 750 students. These children generally
came from wealthy families of rabbis, doctors, and businessmen. The school was
known for its exceptionally high-caliber professors; many of them former university professors or
educators, were fired from public schools due to discriminatory policies.
Stella stood out among her peers for several reasons. Unlike most of the
students, she attended school on a scholarship as she came from a modest background. However
However, his striking appearance attracted considerable attention and with his tall figure
and slim, light blue eyes, blonde hair and perfect skin, she was often compared to the
Hollywood stars. Stella was charismatic and popular, especially with boys.
One day in November 1938, she was sent home early from school, only to
discovering that his father was in hiding because Jewish men were being arrested.
This event became known as the Kristallnacht pogrom, or the Night of the Crystals.
Broken, which was a series of coordinated violent riots against Jews throughout Germany
Nazi and its newly annexed territories on November 9 and 10, 1938.
The violence and arrests marked a turning point for many Jewish families,
including Stella's, as the threat to her safety became increasingly evident.
Stella's father later decided that the time had come for him and his wife
and her daughter to leave the country. However, at that time, emigrating was incredibly difficult
without money or influence. Although the international community was well aware of the growing
persecution of Jews and the Kristallnacht pogrom of 1938 was condemned in
Around the world, almost all countries imposed strict immigration quotas, including the United States.
United. Gerhard Goldschlag was informed at the American consulate that they would spend approximately
two years before his family was allowed entry. Other attempts to emigrate
They also failed, so the Goldschlags had no choice but to remain in Germany.
World War II began on September 1st
from 1939 when Nazi Germany invaded Poland.
At the beginning of the war, Stella enrolled in an art school
where she studied fashion drawing and posed as a nude model for about two years.
In his spare time he sang in a Jewish jazz band and briefly found happiness in the
autumn of 1941, when she married the band's leader, Manfred Kübler. However, like all
Jews, Stella could not escape the rising tide of anti-Semitism. In September 1941,
She was required to wear the Star of David and, that same year, she was forced to work in the
war industry, which temporarily saved her from deportation to a concentration camp.
Initially, Stella was assigned to the Siemens factory that produced electric motors, but
It was then transferred to a munitions plant. On February 27, 1943, during an operation to
large-scale known as "Fabrikaktion", Stella and her mother were caught in a
Jewish raid on their factory. Acting as quickly as possible, they hid in a
makeshift shelter and then left through a back door to evade the guards
the Gestapo. His escape was largely due to his blond hair, which took advantage of the
false belief of the Nazis that Jews could not be blondes. Unfortunately,
Stella's husband, Manfred, was arrested, deported to Auschwitz, and never heard from again.
After the raid, Stella and her parents went into hiding. Samson Schönhaus,
an old friend from art school and long-time admirer of Stella,
operating under the alias Günter Rogoff, forged identity documents for her,
which allowed him to travel without raising suspicion. Rogoff was part of a network
resistance movement made up of Polish Jews and Catholics and had provided at least 40
Jewish prisoners food ration cards, passports and other documents
forged identity cards. Because of his clandestine activities, he was intensively sought by the Gestapo.
On July 2, 1943, while in a bar, Stella was spotted by an acquaintance, Inge Lustig,
a Jewish woman who worked as a Greiferin (i.e., a "hunter" for the Gestapo). Stella was
arrested by Gestapo agents who accompanied Inge and taken to their headquarters at number
26 Burgstrasse. Stella became a prime target for the Gestapo when
They examined her papers and identified them as Rogoff's work. Although she didn't know where
he was there, the Gestapo tried to break her, hoping that she would reveal the whereabouts of her friend.
Stella suffered horrific abuse: her shins were beaten until they broke, she was punched in the
spine repeatedly and was bleeding from the mouth, ears and nose. The interrogators
They pointed the gun at her temple several times, threatening to kill her. Completely devastated,
Stella lost consciousness due to the incessant torture. Even when
She lay helpless on the ground, the Gestapo men continued to kick her.
On July 10, 1943, Stella briefly escaped from the scene during a visit to the dentist, but was
quickly arrested again after seeking refuge in her parents' home, which was under
Gestapo surveillance. After her second capture, she was brutally tortured once again.
On August 24, 1943, the prison where Stella was being held was attacked during a bombing raid.
massive British, which caused widespread panic among the prisoners. However,
While many women perished in the flames, Stella managed to escape.
Instead of running away, Stella voluntarily surrendered at the transit camp.
where her parents were detained, awaiting deportation to Auschwitz. She acted out of love for
his parents, since he had depended heavily on them since his youth,
and was prepared to die with them. This desperate act of love and loyalty
marked the beginning of a heartbreaking chapter in Stella's life. Faced with the harsh reality of the
situation of his family, he made a fateful decision in an attempt to protect his
parents and herself from certain death. To avoid being deported, she and her parents
They agreed to become "hunters", their first task being to locate Günter Rogoff.
However, since she had no real information, she was accused of lying and sent back to
prison. However, an SS agent, Felix Lachmuth, noticed the
Aryan appearance and Stella's intelligence and recruited her as a "hunter" on a permanent basis,
offering certain benefits and ensuring the safety of their parents.
Stella was later trained by the Gestapo to hunt Jews and became part of a unit
formed by about 20 young men and women. Its headquarters were initially located in the countryside
transit area of Grosse Hamburgerstrasse and later moved to the pathology wing
from the Jewish hospital. The bounty hunters were housed in separate rooms
and had access to abundant food. They were rewarded with 300 Reichsmarks.
(the equivalent of about $2,200 today) for each hiding Jew they helped arrest.
They were carrying a weapon and documents identifying them as Gestapo agents.
and were allowed to move freely around the city without wearing the Star of David.
Thanks to his knowledge of many Jewish families and former schoolmates of
During her years at the Goldschmidt School, Stella was very effective in locating them
and betray them to the Gestapo, all while maintaining the appearance of being
hidden. Every time he handed someone over to the Gestapo, he immediately searched the
the victim's bag contained an address book containing the hiding places of other hidden Jews,
which often led to even more arrests. The Nazis referred to her as "the blond poison."
Stella's striking appearance and keen memory for names made her a
an effective hunter. One of her male victims, who survived the war
After escaping from a train to Auschwitz, he recalled how Stella approached him one day and asked him
help. Spending his life in hiding seemed to have taken its toll on him, so he claimed to be hungry.
The man agreed to help her and took her to a pub, where he was led into a trap and arrested for
Gestapo agents. Stella's hunting grounds also included cemeteries. After
that Jewish men or women buried their non-Jewish spouses, Stella denounced them
to the Gestapo, since from then on they were no longer protected by their marriages.
The exact number of Jews captured with Stella's help is unclear,
but it is estimated that there were between 600 and 3,000.
Stella was greatly feared within the community of those who were hidden. According to Inge
Deutschkron, a Holocaust survivor, had a reputation for being able to uncover
Jews and hidden deserters. In the final years of the war, Stella was universally
despised within the Jewish communities and even received death threats.
In the end, the Nazis broke their promise to spare his life.
Stella's parents and in February 1944 they were deported to the Theresienstadt ghetto,
located in the Protectorate of Bohemia and Moravia. Stella begged her superiors to forgive
her parents, but it was in vain. However, after the war she was promised Aryan status
honorary. Her parents were later transported to Auschwitz and murdered.
In October 1944, Stella married her second husband, Rolf Isaaksohn,
a fellow Jewish hunter, but it was not a happy marriage so soon they both began
extramarital affairs. During this time, Stella was not as active as a hunter
because it was too well known to be really effective. In addition, in Berlin there were
few Jews due to the Nazi purges and the zeal of Goldschlag and his compatriots.
In February 1945, Stella became pregnant, probably by her fellow Nazi collaborator
Heino Meisl and, although she expected him to acknowledge paternity and support her and her son
unborn, Meisl disappeared, leaving Stella to fend for herself.
By this point, Stella had lost the support of her lovers and her Nazi superiors, who
were concerned about the Allied advance on the front. In the early stages of the Battle
From Berlin, in April 1945, Stella went into hiding. That same month, she gave birth to her daughter, Yvonne,
in Liebenwalde, a village north of Berlin. The capital fell to the Russians on 2
May 1945 and World War II in Europe ended six days later. While
In 1933 the Jewish population of Berlin was estimated at 160,000 people, at the end of the war only
There were between 1,400 and 1,700 Jews left in the city. They survived because they were well hidden.
After this, the local police arrested Stella and took her son away from her.
and then placed him with adoptive parents. After his arrest, Stella managed to convince
to the police that she was a victim of the Nazis. However, when she was transferred to the community
Berlin Jewish woman for identification, her history was discovered. For the survivors
Jews in Berlin, Stella was the embodiment of evil. After members of the community
A Hebrew woman was almost beaten, insulted and had her head shaved, and was taken to the police station.
Alexanderplatz police station, controlled by the Soviet authorities. After being interrogated,
was brought before a Soviet court. The three judges who heard her case took
just a few minutes to sentence her to 10 years of forced labor.
After serving her sentence, Stella moved to West Berlin to find her daughter,
who lived there with a Jewish family but, due to her dark past, Yvonne
He didn't want anything to do with his mother. Moreover, a year after his release
From the Soviet prison, Stella was accused again, this time for the
West German authorities in Berlin. Stella's second trial began on 20
June 1957 in West Berlin and the press paid much attention to its
activities during the war, calling her "the blonde witch" or "the blonde poison."
She was charged with complicity in the murder of an unknown number of people,
probably a few hundred. The trial lasted four days and the prosecutor called witnesses who described
Stella as a ruthless criminal. Before the trial, a psychiatrist had
diagnosed as a schizophrenic psychopath. Stella tried to arouse sympathy by pointing out
her poor health and her grief over the loss of her son. She denied all charges and
He claimed to be a victim of the times in which he lived. He also argued
that the trial was part of a Jewish conspiracy against her, claiming that the Jews
had always been jealous of her beauty. The court recognized that the collaboration of
Stella's involvement with the Nazis may have initially been motivated by an attempt to save her loved ones.
fathers of deportation. However, he condemned the scope and enthusiasm of their activities,
which continued even after their parents were deported.
Although the prosecution requested 15 years in prison, Stella was sentenced to 10.
Since he had already served 10 years in Soviet prisons, he did not have to return to jail.
After the war, Stella converted to Christianity, married three more times and
became openly anti-Semitic. As he aged, his mental and physical faculties
deteriorated and after the death of her last husband, she led a solitary and isolated existence.
When Stella Goldschlag committed suicide by drowning in the
Moosweiher pond in Freiburg, was 72 years old.
Thanks for watching World History Channel. Don't forget to like it,
Subscribe and click the notification bell so you don't miss out
our next videos. Thanks. See you next time on the channel.